

Zhihao LIU

Nationality: Chinese Date of birth: 25/03/1993

📞 Phone number: (+47) 48648781 🔛 Email address: zhihaol@uio.no

• Home: Olav M. Troviks vei 10, H0412, 0864 OSLO (Norway)

SUMMARY

About me

I am a geomatics professional with 5 years of experience in 12 offshore geophysical surveys. Master's study further enhanced my skills in geostatistics and modeling. My expertise covers a wide range of datasets, including offshore seismic, climate reanalysis, LiDAR, and remote sensing, demonstrating my ability to work across multiple disciplines. I am committed to delivering geodata as a service and providing data-driven solutions. Thus, I am open to all positions related to geodata, particularly in the energy sector after graduation (2023.06)

WORK EXPERIENCE

Research Assistant on Geomatics

UiO [11/2021 - Current]

- 1. Proficient in **Geostatistics and Geospatial Modeling** using Python, with a toolkit including xDEM (coregistration), SciPy (optimizing, interpolation), Rasterio, Shapely, GeoPandas, Multiprocessing, PCA, and Machine learning (XGBoost regression)...
- 2. Worked with a variety of **datasets** including ERA-5, ICESat-2, MODIS, Norway National DTM, and global DEMs (Copernicus, Arctic DEM, etc)
- 3. Experienced in using **GIS tools** such as ArcGIS, QGIS, and automating GIS scripts.

Geomatics Professional

BGP Offshore, China National Petroleum Corporation [07/2014 – 06/2021]

- 1. Participated in over 12 offshore seismic surveys (3D/4D/OBN) as a field technician globally (Norway, UK, West Africa) in a world-class seismic team.
- 2. Scripted data processing pipeline, Optimized workflows through data-driven solutions (my software).
- 3. Took technical responsibilities including contract technical review, patents, and conference publications.
- 4. Registered as a Licensed Surveyor in P.R.C.
- 5. Get promoted to a senior position (2021.01, assistant party chief on seismic vessel).

EDUCATION AND TRAINING

Master in Geoscience

Universitetet i Oslo [15/08/2021 - Current]

Courses (GPA 3.75/4.0):

- 1. Advanced Remote Sensing and Topographic Analysis (A)
- 2. Surveying, Photogrammetry and Spatial Analysis (A)
- 3. Geophysical Data Science (A)
- 4. Glacial and Periglacial Geomorphology
- 5. Floods, Avalanches and Landslides
- 6. IPCC Climate Change 2021-The Physical Science Basis

Thesis: Advancements in Snow Depth Retrieval Using Satellite Altimetry and Machine Learning

Bachelor in Geodesy and Geomatics

South West Petroleum University (China) [09/2010 - 07/2014]

- 1. With a background in Engineering, Cartography, GNSS and GIS (GPA 83/100).
- 2. A for Bachelor's thesis: A WebGIS system for urban infrastructure management

SNOWDEPTH - Global snow depths from spaceborne remote sensing for permafrost, highelevation precipitation, and climate reanalysis

[01/2022 - Current]

Snowmass is key to understanding the snow-depth-related climate mechanism or application, e.g. permafrost thawing, high-mountain precipitation, hydropower...

- 1. Participated in field trip and worked on the ICESat-2 dataset and a variety of DEM products;
- 2. Optimized the popular 'NuthKaab Coregistration' and created one of the best co-registration algorithms: gradient descending coregistration.
- 3. Generated snow depth measurements for the entire of Norway. Now, I am trying to interpolate and feed the data into the climate & hydrological models and contribute my codes to the open-source GIS community.

Skills: Regression, Machine Learning (XBGoost), Terrain Analysis, Spatial Analysis, Multiprocessing, Git

North Sea Quad 35 Hybrid 3D seismic survey

[07/2020 - 11/2020]

Quad 35 is a well-known commercial seismic project in Norway. Historically It combined streamers and node acquisition.

- 1. Worked as a technician for contract technical review, onboard acquisition, data QC & reprocessing, and follow-up work.
- 2. Got the best commendation from the client for modeling this novel acquisition to make it more efficient and understandable.

Skills: Offshore data acquisition, Quality Control, Technical Support, Follow-up

Essaouira side-scan sonar survey, Offshore Morocco

[04/2017 - 04/2017]

The main point of the pre-survey was identifying the possible shallow hazards for the seismic streamers: reefs, shipwrecks, and pipelines.

- 1. Designed and conducted a side-scan sonar pre-survey for seismic projects.
- 2. I am also familiar with offshore magnetic and gravity surveys that we do simultaneously during seismic acquisition.

Skills: Side-scan Sonar, HSEQ, Independent Work

CREATIVE WORKS

Using 5.8 million to buy a unit in Oslo, which one is worth?

The goal of this project was to determine which <u>unit to buy in Oslo</u> using multiple-criteria decision analysis (MCDA). The median price for a unit in the city is 5.8 million.

The project involved scraping property data from Finn, cleaning the data, and gathering spatial information from open-access databases, OpenStreetMap, and satellite images. An MCDA model was then created to make the final decision.

Skills: Web scraping, Spatial Analysis, MCDA Modeling

What if the ice block expedition 1959 happens in 2021?

In 1959, a three-ton block of ice from Mo i Rana by the Arctic Circle was trucked to Libreville by the Equator with an 11% mass loss. Is that true? What if we do it again in 2020 or 2021?

The energy balance model can explain the retreat of the glaciers but also can answer the question here. <u>I applied an energy balance model</u> and coupled ERA 5 with a historical event (the Ice Block Expedition of 1959).

Skills: Numerical Modeling, Climate Reanalysis, Time-series Analysis

How to bury Longyearbyen by an avalanche?

Avalanches are rapid snow mass movements over snow-covered slopes, which could be dangerous for people living in mountainous terrain due to long-time exposure. So, how to bury a town with a designed avalanche?

I used Software RAMMS::Avalanche® to simulate slab avalanche movement by the Voellmy-fluid friction model. I found NVE's new report may overestimate the size of the avalanche in some scenarios.

Skills: Mass Movement Modeling, GIS

CONFERENCES AND SEMINARS

Unlocking the secrets of snow depth - a study of satellite altimetry and high-precision digital elevation models

Oral presentation at Sustainability Conference 2023, UiO

Wide-towed sources in streamer seismic: a case study from Norway Q35

Zhihao Liu, Bo Wen, Yuanjie Liu, Xuebin Qin, Qian Zhao, <u>Conference paper</u> from Society of Petroleum Geophysicists 2021, Chengdu, China

A hybrid seismic acquisition: from wide-towed sources, sparse node to FWI

Zhihao Liu, Yuanjie Liu, Bo Wen, BGP geophysical technology overseas workshop 2021, Beijing, China (not open access)

An identification system for underwater seismic devices

Patent, PRC 201911154941X · Issued May 13, 2022.

Offshoreorinet v1.0 Offshore seismic QC software

Software Copyright, 2020SR0194691 · Issued Mar 2, 2020.

LANGUAGE SKILLS

Mother tongue(s): Chinese

Other language(s): English (professional working proficiency) | Norsk (beginner)

HOBBIES AND INTERESTS

Marathon

- 1. Not bad runner with 130 (half-marathon) and 330 (marathon) of the personal best.
- 2. Have organized medium size marathon (15K) and was in charge of supply and volunteers.

OSI Friluft (volunteer)

- 1. Board member Media & Facebook.
- 2. Tour leader of outdoor.

REFERENCES

2021 - Present

Professor and Supervisor, Andreas Max Kääb, Email: a.m.kaab@geo.uio.no, Mobile: +47 22855812

Project Leader and Co-supervisor, <u>Désirée Treichler</u>, Email: <u>desiree.treichler@geo.uio.no</u>, Mobile: +47 22857869

2016 - 2021

Chief geophysicist of BGP Prospector, Bo Wen, Email: wenbo01@cnpc.com.cn, Mobile: +86 18622259275

25/02/2023